George Ernest Barnett Papers 5223
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
George Ernest Barnett Papers
1911-1914
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Barnett, George Ernest
5223
2.67 cubic feet
2.7 linear ft.
First drafts, statistics.
Largely files of correspondence (1911-1914) relating to the United States Commission on Industrial Relations' study on the growth of trade union membership in the United States and the extent of organization in various occupations and trades.
3834362
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
CB, January 06, 2004
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 21, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Commission on Industrial Relations was established by Act of Congress on August 23, 1912. The Commission's charge was to "inquire into the general condition of labor in the principal industries of the United States, including agriculture, and especially in those which are carried on in corporate forms ...; into the growth of associations of employers and of wage earners and the effect of such associations upon the relations between employers and employees ..." among other duties.
Professor George E. Barnett of Johns Hopkins University and Leo Wolman, a Ph.D. candidate at Johns Hopkins, were hired by the Commission to investigate several matters relating to union membership and the specific nature of several collective bargaining agreements. Dr. Wolman later went on to become a professor of economics specializing in labor and industrial relations at Columbia University.
Scope and Contents
Correspondents are Dr. George E. Barnett and Leo Wolman (special agents of the Commission) with the majority of trade unions affiliated with the American Federation of Labor and a number of independent unions. Barnett initiated the study and supervised Wolman in completing the project. Included is a manuscript first draft of the resulting report entitled "The Extent of Organization in the United States in 1910," including manuscript and printed occupational and census tables. Also a file of constitutions, by-laws, agreements and rules of order for the San Francisco trade unions and the San Francisco Labor Council (1907- 1913) and several reprints of articles by Barnett (1916-1926).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Independent unions -- United States -- Membership; Industrial relations -- Research -- United States; Occupational surveys.; Labor unions -- California -- San Francisco; Labor unions -- United States -- Membership; Labor unions -- United States -- Statistics; Occupational characteristics. United States.; United States. Occupations.; Barnett, George Ernest, 1873-1938.; Wolman, Leo, 1890-1961; American Federation of Labor; Associated Union of Steam Shovelmen; Brewers Protective Association; Brotherhood of Railroad Building Mechanics of America; Industrial Workers of the World; International Association of Machinists; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; International Molders and Allied Workers' Union; International Union of United Brewery, Flour, Cereal, Soft Drink, and Distillery Workers of America; Iron Trade Council of San Francisco and Vicinity; Journeymen Tailors' Union of North America; Laborer's Protective Unions; Merchants and Manufacturers Association; San Francisco Beer Bottlers Board of Trade; San Francisco Labor Council; Stable Employees Union; United States. Commission on Industrial Relations.; United Textile Workers of America
3834362
- Correspondence, 1914-1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Primarily to and by Leo Wolman
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Independent local unions
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Replies and data received from union in the U.S.C.I.R. Study of 1914
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Replies, etc.
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Wolman letters, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Wolman letters, 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Wolman letters, 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Data on the San Francisco Trade Unions (Box 3, Folder 3)
  File I Introduction
- Data on the San Francisco Trade Unions (Box 3, Folder 4)
  File II - Brewery Trades of San Francisco
- Data on the San Francisco Trade Unions (Box 3, Folder 5)
  File III - Metal Trades of San Francisco
- Data on the San Francisco Trade Unions (Box 3, Folder 6)
  File IV - Teaming Trades of San Francisco
- First Draft of the Report (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Raw Data and Memoranda (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Tables (Printed) (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Tables (Printed) (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Publications (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Scrapbook of Leo Wolman articles (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Mostly from New Republic